when I first tried flutter a few years
ago when it was in beta I instantly
loved it because it made mobile app
development so much faster but nowadays
in 2023 flutter development is like 10
times faster than it was thanks to
visual editing magic would you like to
see a magic trick in today's video I'll
show you exactly how I'm building my own
native IOS and Android apps but instead
of writing all The Code by hand like
I've always done in the past I fully
embraced the productivity boost of a
visual editor called flutter flow the
sponsor of today's video but please
don't tell them I would have made this
video for free because the product is
really that good and as you may know I'm
always highly skeptical of Loco tools
because they often produce garbage code
then you hit a brick wall when you need
something custom but that's not the case
with flutter flow in the next five
minutes we'll build a full Stack mobile
app that handles user authentication
along with real-time data and firestore
when you first sign up it has a demo app
so let's first do a quick tour of the
most important features a flutter app is
structured as a tree of widgets in the
middle we have our canvas where we can
Traverse these widgets flutter provides
a bunch of built-in widgets that we can
actually just grab here from the sidebar
then drag and drop them into the UI
visually then once you have a widget
selected you can go to the right side
and update its properties like alignment
padding colors Shadows background images
and all kinds of other stuff that's a
huge productivity boost right there but
many widgets need to be interactive for
that we can go to the actions tab and
then choose an event like on double tap
that will run some code when this event
is fired we might navigate to another
page close a dialog or even make a call
to firestore or some other API we can
also easily add animations when actions
are triggered on top of that we can
document each widget which will insert a
comment into the code and speaking of
the code we can view it by clicking this
code button up here that'll take us to
the code view where we can view the
source code for an entire page or we can
click on an individual widget to
highlight just that code and as an
experienced letter developer I feel like
I understand what this code does but one
of the more complicated aspects of
development is State Management on the
sidebar here we have our app state which
allows you to organize Global state that
can be used anywhere in the application
in addition we can make this state
persisted which will store it on device
between sessions we can use it in the
application like by setting it as the
text field on the button then from there
we can create an action to update the
state and have the entire application
react to it but you don't want all data
to be Global if we click on the widget
tree here in the sidebar you'll notice
that we can select every page in the
application pages are special because
they can be navigated to with the router
but they also have the option to have
their own State you'll notice a state
management button here on the right
where we can add stateful variables to
it that's cool but you might also have
individual widgets that have their own
local state as the widget tree grows
more complex you'll want to break it
down into your own custom components
that can be reused you can do that by
selecting a point in the widget tree
then right click and convert to
component or just click on the diamond
icon what's awesome is that you can now
edit this component in isolation and it
can Define its own local state it's all
very logical and you don't need to think
about implementing some complex State
management system if we look at the code
it generates a model file for the data
itself then uses built-in flutter
Primitives like setstate to update this
data in the application now the next
thing I want to show you is the theme
editor from this panel we can customize
the design system like responsive
breakpoints colors and typography and
you can also manage custom fonts and
icons here as well all the features I've
showed you up until this point will
likely take care of 90 percent of your
UI and state management needs however at
some point you'll likely need to write
custom code like maybe you have a widget
you want to reuse from a different
project or maybe you just have some
custom dark function that does some
fancy math the custom code panel allows
you to write that code and then apply it
in the application visually oh and what
do we have here an open AI panel that
can write this code for you this thing
is ridiculously overpowered and if that
weren't enough we can also write unit
tests for this code visually to make
sure that we're actually getting valid
code there's a ton of other features we
could talk about here but now I want to
take you behind the scenes and show you
how I'm using it to build a native
mobile app for fireship pro members the
fireship website uses Firebase as the
back end and one thing that's especially
awesome about flutter flow is that it
integrates with Firebase as well as
super bass out of the box when you
create a new project you can actually
just give it your Firebase project ID
and add flutter flow as an Editor to
your project and it will automatically
generate all of your config files as
well as Firebase rules and things like
that it eliminates a lot of tedious
configuration work now once you have the
project set up you can actually create a
schema for your data and firestore and
this allows you to use that data model
anywhere in the flutter app on top of
that it even has a schema validation
tool to make sure that the schema
actually matches up with the data in the
database now if you're not using
Firebase you can also make API calls and
then use Json path as a query language
for example if you have an existing next
JS app with API routes you could call
those API routes to bring in data to
your flutter app or any other API for
that matter but here's where things
start to get really cool as you can see
here I have a login page to use the
application we've got multiple sign-in
methods and usually that's a lot of work
to get all coded up because normally you
would log in create a document in
firestore for that user and then
navigate to the appropriate screen well
we can actually handle that entire
process without writing any code if we
click on a button and then go to the
actions it'll take us to the action flow
editor in this case we want to implement
Google sign in so we just choose their
Google auth provider and we're done in
many cases though you may also want to
create a document and firestore when the
user signs up we can do that
automatically by checking the box for
create collection but once the user is
authenticated we then need to navigate
to a page we can handle that by adding a
second action to this flow we'll tell it
to navigate to our profile page and we
can even throw in a sliding animation
here if we want but what if the logic
here is even more complex like maybe we
want to do one thing for pro members and
do something entirely different for
non-pro members we can handle that by
adding a condition now that the user is
authenticated we have access to the
state of the user and we can Branch off
our workflow based on whether or not
that user is a pro member from there
each user could be navigated to a
different screen or we could even add
additional backend calls here to one of
the API routes or to firestore to create
a new document and that's all it takes
to log in a user with complex backend
logic oh and one other thing I want to
point out here is that the actual UI for
the sign in buttons was not designed by
me personally but came from one of
flutterflow's built-in templates you can
just drag these right into the camera
canvas and tweak their settings and if
you're building multiple flutter apps
you can create what are called theme
widgets you reuse your own widgets
across multiple projects and that's a
huge feature if you run an agency that
creates apps for other people in any
case when a user logs in as a pro member
I want to take them to a profile page
that shows their Pro status as well as
their total experience points you might
be wondering though how and where do we
fetch this data well you can handle data
fetching at any point in the widget tree
but in this case we'll do it at the page
level when we click on the page widget
we can then find the button for backend
query which allows us to create a query
that could either grab a single document
from firestore a collection from
firestore or make an API call to some
other service in this case we just want
to fetch a single document from the
user's collection that's linked to the
currently logged in user by default it
will use Firebase real-time features to
update the document whenever A Change Is
Made although you can change that
behavior by making it a one-time query
and now that we have that data we can
start using it throughout the
application all the values in Brackets
like Pro status display name and total
XP are based on the firestore schema
that we we set up earlier if you're
wondering how that works we can look at
the code and see here that it has a
stream Builder wrapped around the entire
page and that's the exact way I would
set it up if I were doing it myself in
the code but now let's go to the
achievements page which makes a query to
a firestore collection it's the same
basic process but we can do additional
things here like filtering and ordering
on the firestore query one thing I find
extra cool here is that you'll notice we
have four different elements in the list
and that's because it auto populates
those to give you a preview of what it
should look like when you fetch your
data but now let's assume we're ready to
run our application and then deploy it
to the App Stores the first thing we can
do is click on the eyeball to go into
preview mode in preview mode it won't
actually fetch your data but things like
navigation will work so you can get the
general idea of how things are looking
on a variety of different devices now to
actually run the app we can click on the
lightning bolt to test it in the browser
this works pretty well but not all
features are supported in the browser
like the device camera vibration and
stuff like that another option is to
download the actual code and run it
locally in Android Studio or xcode and
when it comes to Android you can
actually build and download the APK
directly this is a paid feature but if
you're serious about deploying a native
app it's money well spent and if you go
to the settings tab it integrates with
codemagic for one-click deployment to
the App Stores but even if you're not
serious the free tier is a great way to
get things built quickly and also just a
great way to learn flutter to see how
different patterns can be implemented
the reason I'm using it to build my app
though is because it writes code that I
understand and like and just eliminates
a ridiculous amount of friction like I
didn't even talk about push
notifications app permissions or
multilingual support all of which can
also be handled by flutter flow thanks
for watching and I will see you in the
next one